<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[gudhakesa]]></title><description><![CDATA[gudhakesa]]></description><link>http://gudhakesa.com</link><image><url>/images/post1.jpg</url><title>gudhakesa</title><link>http://gudhakesa.com</link></image><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2018 13:09:53 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://gudhakesa.com/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[In faith of digital]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>Story of Startups and Technology</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Startups equal technology. These are the things millennials all over the world start talking about. From a coworking space in the western side of Bali, up to a hip San Fransisco district called silicon valley. It&#8217;s been used a lot, the words association seem stickier than a gum on your hair.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>But what&#8217;s a startup, essentially?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>A business model experimentation. Yeah, that&#8217;s the word I&#8217;ll use. It&#8217;s a bunch of people bonded in a legal bond called a "company", trying out new stuff to experiment a business model that can reach a large market in just a few years (and this is fast for a scaled-up multinational company, if they make it). Trying to reach that amount of market size (or some people say "traction"), is indeed challenging. Resources need to be burned in order to create infrastructure that are capable of sustaining that (hopefully) big market size. And this is why money and capital matters.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>And talking about "infrastructure", it&#8217;s no debate, that technology (thanks to internet, interconnectivity, smartphones, and cheaper data plan) is indeed one of the most effective way to make sure the company "gain traction". I said one of the most effective because somehow I don&#8217;t believe it&#8217;s the only way. Especially if you&#8217;re sitting in a country called Indonesia. One of the largest third world country which growth now higher than South Korea, thanks to its micro segment.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>Leveraging current practices</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>So what&#8217;s going on there? Well, let&#8217;s study the exhibits. We all know that company like Go-Jek soar and made it up to the New York headlines a couple of years ago. The success story about creating a digital product to leverage an ongoing practice of motorcycle taxis took the market by storm, and suddenly now people in big urban city like Jakarta now depend their daily lives to this services.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>At the surface level, yes, we know this company leverage technology and online. But I think the more important matter we should look is the way the practice of motorcycle taxis work as an ongoing practice. The power of that company is actually on the established practice of the motorcycle taxis. The technology is only leveraged to make sure that the entire customer process of getting a motorcycle taxi service is paved smoother.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The business is genius, because it acknowledge a behavior that existed, and the technology just scales up the entire practices. Copy it to other region, and there you have it. Big success.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>Realities, realities</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Position yourself as a business consultant that deals with people getting hyped up with technology and digital products. Now you&#8217;re in my position.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The work is of course, damn interesting. Always a new way to experiment new models and approach in trying to reach a scalable market in short time. The goal is to create a pathway for consumers to use your products, whatever it is, and gain something out of it for them to happily use it again. You&#8217;re improving people&#8217;s lives here. You&#8217;re making an impact. Do I sound like a millennial already?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>But it turns out, sometimes, this goal is hard to achieve. Why? Let me get there soon.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The problem here is just I&#8217;ve seen a lot of people trying to create products or a solution just for the sake of creating a solution. And they&#8217;re doing so, creating these solutions for problems that don&#8217;t exist in the first place. And why do I start to feel like this is a generational problem?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>What happened is, people forget about the current practices. Especially the ones the target consumer is doing. One of my headaches working with young startup people now is they don&#8217;t really care about the lives of their users. Their focus is more on the things they imagine the users have, without having to check whether that&#8217;s a problem the user really have. Talk about failure to do market validation here. Trying to create food delivery service for bicycle couriers. Where do you think we live? China?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The other thing is, sometimes I face people who forget that not every demographic of the user are ready for digital. Yes, I KNOW that digitalization is inevitable somehow. The future lies in digital and big data. But when can we learn that not all, I repeat, NOT ALL demographics are ready for this? At least if you create a digital product to reach this unready market, why don&#8217;t we create a roadmap instead of a "digital product"?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I think, this is the most difficult part of the job. Not about creating opportunities, but having to face people whose ideologies in creating a startup business went against the fundamental of creating a user-centric product. When they&#8217;re creating things that simply solve a problem that doesn&#8217;t exist, the worse part of the job is actually having to tell people about it in their faces.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>Next step forward</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>If there is one design question I&#8217;d like to solve, I think it would be "How might we make startup creator (clients) to be more grounded in creating their product plan (or simply to be smarter)". Sorry man. I need to say it sometimes. Clients could be just as stupid as an ungrounded freshman of a fucked-up business school.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>But then again, I don&#8217;t blame them. The changes in this world, is just too damn fast, I presume. We&#8217;ve seen development of business and innovation at a rate that is faster than traditionally schooled, well-educated, middleclassmen can perceive. Who knows what are the things possible achieving in the near future. We&#8217;re simply trying our best to navigate the waters of innovation steadily, with all the best knowledge we have. The future is still uncharted, and we try our best to make sense of the seas ahead based on our previous wisdoms and practices.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I think it&#8217;s important for us, whatever business we are in, to have a reboot at our understanding on how to create and make business work. Our understanding of business wisdom needs to change, and it needs to be the central point in our endeavor. No, your skills and experience as a back (or front) end developer won&#8217;t do you any good, won&#8217;t help you make good products, if you can&#8217;t focus yourself on the reality of your potential users, or if you can&#8217;t admit openly that your hypothesis is entirely off.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Digital platforms are only tools. Enablers. Enablers for people to achieve something, something they are familiar of. And to understand their main motive and goals is central in creating a digital product that works seamlessly. This understanding of the end user should be the quintessence of a design discipline. And I do think we should start from there.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Don&#8217;t be an overly hyped up startup person. Startups are costly and expensive to develop. It takes resilience and hardwork, and not forgetting good timing. It takes passion and a belief that products are solving user&#8217;s problems. But sometimes, fundamentally, it does takes a good observation skills and a bit of intelligence to make it work. Groom some.</p>
</div>]]></description><link>http://gudhakesa.com/2018/01/31/the-digital-blind-faith.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gudhakesa.com/2018/01/31/the-digital-blind-faith.html</guid><category><![CDATA[words]]></category><category><![CDATA[ research]]></category><category><![CDATA[ business]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Mahendra Gudhakesa]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Dissecting Empathy]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>In my line of work, the word "Empathy" gets thrown out a lot. We all have quick and easy definition on what&#8217;s the meaning of the word. But what is it really? What is the true measure of empathy? We heard it just as often in seminars or public talks. But what does it mean when we say that designers, creators should have empathy?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Is there any structured effort in establishing empathy? How can we acquire empathy to people we&#8217;re trying to reach?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I think this should make a good topic for this piece, about establishing empathy. Although this is a not-scholarly definitions and what-to-dos, I treat this as a quick and dirty approach to establish empathy. An informal checklist that we can use together to put ourselves more in other people&#8217;s shoes. Especially useful if you&#8217;re a designer, or marketer, or even some propaganda mastermind.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>An ethnographic approach on life fields &amp; personal values</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I believe that empathy is the byproduct of deep understanding. A holistic understanding of one&#8217;s life realities, so that we could position ourselves in one&#8217;s point of view. It&#8217;s a discipline of internalizing other people&#8217;s internal beliefs so that it could broaden our horizon of many different lifeforms. And this is something that is in line with the discipline of ethnography. Empathy then, for me as an ethnographer, is more about understanding three things: Activities, Goals, and Personal Values.</p>
</div>
<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="http://gudhakesa.com/images/qual/Light1.jpg" alt="Light1.jpg">
</div>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>Understanding one&#8217;s activity and goals</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Among us people in the modern age, there are three domains (or life fields) that constantly demand our attention: The domestic domain, professional domain, and leisure.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Domestic domains are the life field in which we spend our resources (time, money, energy) on the people closest to us. Families, friends, house life, children, parents, and so on. I believe that we spent our time growing up from kids to adults with more emphasis on this domain.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The more we get older, we assign expertise to ourselves. We do things to contribute to the world, to work, to create value, and to earn our living. These activities rest in the professional domain. It&#8217;s a collection of activities and resources spent on work and making a living.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Leisure, is a life field where we spend our excess resources. The things we do for our own personal entertainment. The things we enjoy doing that contributes to our day-to-day psychological well-being, some might say.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>To understand the life reality of others, for me, is to dive deep, look closer on one&#8217;s three domains. What are the activities spent on each domain? How does one do his / her activity in those three domains? And the more important question: what do they want to achieve in each domain when they do those activities? What are the things they want to achieve when doing that?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>A deep understanding on people&#8217;s activity helps us to understand the realities of one&#8217;s life. It&#8217;ll be easy for us to imagine what kind of experience one have to deal with, and what kind of struggle (s)he has on a daily basis. We could at least imagine, what are the things that give constraints to their decision making? What are the things that happen to be the foundation on their life&#8217;s orbit?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Diving deeper to these sets of activities could also enable our understanding on one&#8217;s personal values.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>What makes a personal value / worldview?</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I think I&#8217;d like to view personal values as a set of mental beliefs that drives the direction of one&#8217;s goals and achievements. I like how the movie "Inside Out" by Disney portray what they call "Island of personality". Personal values are the byproduct of those so-called "island of personality", in which it drives our decision making process and life priorities.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>To assess one&#8217;s personal values is to assess at least the background stories behind their activities. Since when do they start doing that activity? Why those activities are chosen and done routinely? What are the factors that drives their intention to those activities?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The last question is actually quite an interesting thing to explore. Intention. Psychology had explored this theme long ago with the invention of intention theory, which said that intention is driven by 3 major factors: <strong>Subjective belief</strong> (their personal belief on what makes one activity important doing), <strong>significant other&#8217;s belief</strong> (their significant other&#8217;s take on the importance of one activity), and <strong>perceived behavioral control</strong> (external factors that drive up intention of doing one activity).</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Exploring these factors, along with checking their background experiences that drive those beliefs are crucial in understanding why they behave like they do.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>Reflections</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>This approach, of course, is not a one-for-all approach. Nor this is the only way to really give structure and meaning of the word "empathy". But deep exploration on these topics hopefully can give us a guide on pointing out the areas of people&#8217;s lives we could touch and understand. And of course, understanding this approach is not not only helpful to understand other people, but also to stop and look at ourselves. Where are we at the moment. How did we manage to think like we do now?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>When we do this approach more often, we will start seeing pattern. Like, in observation of the activities in the three domain, I now realize that no people actually excel in all three domains. Out of the three domains, people usually succeeds only at two domains. When people&#8217;s domestic life and professional thrive, people might think that they don&#8217;t have time for leisure. When we see people who succeeded or fulfilled professionally and in leisure time. It&#8217;s normal to suspect that one will not be so fulfilled in his domestic life.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Empathy. I think it&#8217;s not a tool or a word that serve us to know other people, but understanding it, also to give us opportunity to know ourselves better. We become more accepting not only to other people, but we could start tolerating things that could happen to our lives.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>And that&#8217;s why I believe, that empathy, is more about self awareness rather than mere "understanding others".</p>
</div>]]></description><link>http://gudhakesa.com/2018/01/30/understanding-empathy.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gudhakesa.com/2018/01/30/understanding-empathy.html</guid><category><![CDATA[words]]></category><category><![CDATA[ qualitative]]></category><category><![CDATA[ research]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Mahendra Gudhakesa]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 30 Jan 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[The stoic's journal]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>Just fifteen minutes towards midnight. I lay in my bed for hours now, trying to shut down my brain for a good night sleep. But my consciousness seem to have another idea. I can’t turn those thoughts off. Those train of random thoughts and event running around like race horses on steroids.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>My existential being betraying my body. The harder I close my eyes, the more the images in my head explode with colors. The harder I put effort to shut my mind down, the more vivid those questions arise. Magnificent.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I thought about my days lately. It wasn’t that much fun, but it’s normal. It’s just the way it is. Fun days are overrated. To hope that everyday is filled with joy, enjoyment of work, or fulfilling achievement is so hollywood like. Something you could only find in sitcoms or romcoms. No, life is just as normal as it should be. Like rainy seasons, it happens in certain time of year. Rain is there, it will pour. We predict rain, we prepare ourselves for it. Just like we should prepare our days with betrayal, irony, disappointment. It’s all there, a natural change of seasons…</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>What are dreams or plans? What significance it brings to our psyche? What sense of safety do they evoke in us? Do they even work at all, I wonder… Why do we hope for good things to happen? When the meaning of life is to endure and to walk on? I have strayed upon the path of comfort and security, for it has robbed me from freedom and simplicity.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The people who are close to us, have the tendency to stab us in the back of our head. They will disappoint, they will kill our characters, they will rob us from our dignity.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Our lovers will stray, or they will doom us to loneliness. They will run around with our fragile hearts, tossing playfully with trials and experiments. They will sometimes put ours aside, making room for other hearts to be tossed and played around. In its most optimistic scenario, they will try to cage ourselves within the boundaries of institution and beliefs, trying to make the world go round with the word “us” as the navel of universe.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Stray, oh stray, we will all be.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>But do all of those things matter? Aren’t they just a part of life? And don’t we all have control over our ways? We could say no, we could turn back,  we could abandon, and we could just walk on. It is the essence of life. A journey of decisions and steps taken, but never to turn back. It is a journey of detours and closed opportunities, but never we can stop.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I believed, once in my life, that I am free. Freer than i thought I am.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>With freedom comes the utmost consequence, and that is choice. Oh the irony of choice. The byproduct of freedom that also robs us from freedom itself. We are freer than we could ever thought, but we are never for once free from regrets and consequences. Then what really lies in the definition of freedom? What lie does the word contains, which fools ourselves to chase the mirage of happiness at the end of the rainbow. Rainbows, then, never really touch the ground.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The world revolves around its axis. Along with its ever changing seasons and storms. We are never free. We are doomed with our choices, with clocks ticking awaiting for us to make one, tick-tock, tick-tock. And life holds its utmost reward, for people who sticks to their choices…</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>We are all, part of life’s journey. We are part of other people’s choices. We are free, but never in ways we thought we were…We are free to adapt and adjust. The only essence of freedom we were given, at the consequence of our choices. We are at the very end, free to associate, to disassociate ourselves with the things that matter. We are free to define what, and how, things or people matter to us. And we constantly abide to that rule, that we will always have to decide, decide, decide… We are free to decide, but we should continuously, vigorously, decide, decide, and decide… For decisions, is the only way we step forward. Holding ground, is not life’s way.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Oh the sin of memories! How it shackles our ankles from moving forward. How sentimental the images we once had in our heads, that stray us from the path we wanted to walk upon. Oh deadly memories, thou shall walk me in circles! Thou art like cyanide. A poison of life. Memories, are stories. It soothes, it’s retold. It detaches us. It disconnects, it distorts. Is the essence of being free to live, lies within us being free from our memories?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Oh lies, lies, and lies… If only lies are a person, for me to hold its neck with my bare hands. Or should I just be blind from its frolic and amusement? Then what is the cost of holding a grudge towards it? How will it benefit me, holding the truth for the sake of politeness…</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>It rains outside. Rainy days happen. It’s a sign of life. Just like disappointment, betrayal, or hate. It’s a change of seasons. We are never going to be free from its pouring over our heads. And I assure myself, mankind are made to get through such adversities. We are always at the power to endure. And we will be okay…</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>“We will be okay… “</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I drift away to darkness. I fall asleep under that blissful spell…</p>
</div>]]></description><link>http://gudhakesa.com/2018/01/01/a-late-night-thought.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gudhakesa.com/2018/01/01/a-late-night-thought.html</guid><category><![CDATA[words]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Mahendra Gudhakesa]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Gen-Y, The Paradox Of Abundance And Why We Should Read More History]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>There&#8217;s nothing Gen-Y is more proud of than being a part of Gen-Y. Let&#8217;s recap our lives a little: We&#8217;ve seen faster-growing societal development than most generations have. It took us probably less than a decade to see the world changes in front of our eyes.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>We&#8217;re the lucky generation, and we are accustomed to change. We&#8217;re the generation that is spoon-fed uncertainties and guided by cluelessness.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>We&#8217;re the generation whose 20-somethings have the hardest time making sense of life, yet we&#8217;re also the generation that is most self-absorbed, self-reflective and the most self-contained.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>We&#8217;re the generation that faces the constant friction between society&#8217;s expectations and our inner values. We&#8217;re the generation of earned substance.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>We&#8217;re the generation that&#8217;s the most rebellious against the status quo. We speak up to our parents just because. We fight with them and we learn to make our own decisions.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>On that point, it&#8217;s obvious to see that the future of the world is within our reach. It&#8217;s our responsibility to drive ourselves and our society to a better world than we all imagined.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Information is a single click away, a touch away or even a glance away. Self-enrichment is no longer a question of access, but a question of mere determination. The treasures and riches of the world are now hiding beneath our plain sight.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>But the downside is that we do realize we&#8217;re a generation with an attention span shorter than that of Dory the fish (and we are a generation that gets that reference). Our generation is often considered to be the generation of historical oblivion.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Previous generations often complain about how easy it is now to have access to vast array of information, yet we pretty much don&#8217;t care about using it. The beginning of a borderless society is not that far on the horizon, yet we&#8217;re hardly prepared.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Aren&#8217;t we though? We could list reasons and arguments in defense of those accusations, but maybe we&#8217;ll save it for another story. Now, if we dig deeper under that accusation, maybe we&#8217;ll be able to ask, are we really doing the right thing at all?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Are we really growing how we&#8217;re supposed to grow? Are we restless enough in trying to shape society how it&#8217;s meant to be shaped? Could history or past wisdom really get us somewhere?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I could agree that often, what&#8217;s missing from our generation is our uneasiness, curiosity and inquisitiveness in the midst of mediocrity and straight trajectories.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>We&#8217;re often trapped by dwelling inside our comfort zones. We get too focused on realizing that the world is indeed better than previous times, so we settle. But, we forget that the world is changing, and fast.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I&#8217;ve been lucky enough to be in an industry and social environment where things like these are the daily topics of conversation between peers and fellow professionals.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>As me and my peers strive to move forward in our business, or even try to set our place within the society, we realize that advancement is difficult to accomplish. And sadly, we&#8217;re who gets in our own way.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I&#8217;ve heard a lot of business practitioners out there complaining about the overall attitude of Generation-Y, which they define as the so-called "paradox of abundance."</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The paradox of abundance goes like this: Think of you being seated in a buffet restaurant where you can have everything you could ever imagine, served on the table in front of you. Yes, we could have it all; unfortunately what we don&#8217;t have is the appetite.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Think of all the things we could get so easily now in life. Information, skills and collaboration are right under our noses, and probably just a data-plan away.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Yet we feed our short attention spans with disproportionate amounts of endless cat videos and a dresses of blue or gold.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>What are we looking for in life? Are we busy trying to make ourselves look cool with our wide range of activities? Are we busy feeding our interest with entertaining-yet-mind-dulling gossip we love to share during our lunch conversations?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Are we really so deprived of ideas to discuss about in our spare time that we now seek small things to talk about over one-line messages?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Are we busy enough expressing ourselves with brands and products we see making their way into the furthest corner of the world?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Deep inside, I am sure, despite all these distractions and lack of focus, we&#8217;ll get it right some day or somehow. Cluelessness and distractions are natural parts of a Generation-Yer&#8217;s life.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Maybe we need that cluelessness to take our generation into its ideal full form in society.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Maybe we need those distractions to give us more serendipity in life. It&#8217;s not wrong to slow down a little, seek out information and make sense of those wisdoms of our past so we could be more sensitive in determining our own life&#8217;s success stories. Eventually though, isn&#8217;t there nothing new under the sun?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The industrial revolution had shaped our society into the capitalist force it is today, but the world is moving toward the borderless society through technology.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Start-ups and business incubators made their way, creating things we&#8217;ve never seen before, yet sending us back into the old artisan, pre-industrial economic era.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>We dream of making the world free from hunger. We want to make the planet more habitable, and we want to leave a better place for our children, just like the hippies from the mid-60s.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>If we plunge ourselves a little bit more into the stories of the past, or if we study our history in a little more perseverant manner, maybe we could make sense of the future.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>We do realize, though, our life context expanded into unknown realms and our narratives do not evolve that much across decades or centuries. Our experiences have already been written about.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>So, why don&#8217;t we start being a little less oblivious and plunge ourselves into the past? Maybe it&#8217;ll help bring about the utopian society about which we only previously dreamed.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Maybe we should humble ourselves once in a while and listen to what those old folks are trying to say.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>For us to really change the world, maybe it&#8217;s time we read more books, be a little more curious be more inquisitive and to cherish our time by respecting what our forefathers had envisioned back then. Maybe after that, we&#8217;ll be ready to put up with our current challenges to make this world a better place.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>This article is originally published in elitedaily.com on March 19, 2015</strong></p>
</div>]]></description><link>http://gudhakesa.com/2017/09/29/Why-Gen-Y-should-read-more-history.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gudhakesa.com/2017/09/29/Why-Gen-Y-should-read-more-history.html</guid><category><![CDATA[words]]></category><category><![CDATA[ millennials]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Mahendra Gudhakesa]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 29 Sep 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[The (post)Modern Pilgrimage]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="quoteblock">
<blockquote>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I am not naturally expressive when it comes to certain topics, especially topics about religion and faiths. I understood that faiths and religion should be a very personal matter. It should governs your relationship and your relationship only with the supreme being / the universe / with people around you. Yet, I hope that the things I wrote below, could also be a voice for more people in distress…</p>
</div>
</blockquote>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I am a Moslem. I am not born a moslem, I am not an indoctrinated moslem. I am one of the few lucky people in Indonesia who are nurtured in multicultural family, and I am more than lucky to be a moslem by choice. Not by doctrine.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I embrace the teachings of Islam. But I am also one of the growing number of Millennials who are starting to question their faiths.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>No, I am not questioning about the relevance or truth behind the holy book. I am not questioning the true historical nature of the prophet or the holy men before me. I embrace the teaching as my philosophy of life, and in fact, I hold dear to its values.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I currently stop to publicly announce my faith, or to publicly do my rituals. I don’t publicly announce whether I still do my prayers or not. I stopped going to Friday prayers not because I don’t believe in its importance, but I rather not endorse it the way it’s conducted in my local community.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Long story short, I am simply questioning the real reason my local society is currently adopting this faith.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>Local Stories…</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>In a country which have the combination of having the largest moslem population on earth, and also having the widest gap between modern and traditional societies, it is well understood that Islam had embed itself on majority of our social construct for ages.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>In social context, the history of Islam in Indonesia had not been free from political agendas, propaganda, indoctrinations, and also local adaptations. Although Indonesia by design isn’t a moslem country, the teachings of Islam had arguably infiltrate most of our sociocultural values upon which a perceived good functioning society stands for. It is practised, endorsed, not for mere personal governance, but also becomes a measurement for good-functioning society.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Unlike many high-profile countries, which ground its societal standing based on a deliberate focus on humanitarian rights, this country seem to have customised its social consuetude based on mix of local common sense and literal religion repercussions.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Although some local Islamic societies do practice a modern and progressive approach towards its understanding of teachings, some other societies still think that Allah (our God) is a totalitarian dictatorship, in which His words are to be practised as it is, word by word. Or else, suffer the consequences.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>This fact alone had jeopardized our society by segmenting the faith itself into many sets of localities based on each local interpretations. The verse of the holy book are universal and in uniform. Some believers (if not most), are simply lost in translations…</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>There are no longer universal Islam. It’s only a postmodernist faith with (almost) no grand narrative, segmented by glitch in how we communicate. The dream to unite all men under the “same faith” now sounds like an oxymoron.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>Juxtaposing Progress and Anachronistic Changes</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The development of world civilizations could not be avoided. Progress is the intermediary cause of change in developing-countries like Indonesia. Often times, changes were never smooth across societies. And here, cultural conflicts seemed to be the most prominent shades in these changes.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Cultural conflicts usually happen in these scenarios: Modern society had empowered certain religion-powered-societies, which enable them to rise in power, or to have firmer stand within our social construct. The stronger the forces of modernizations, the tougher they stand to the values they once believed in. It’s part of the science of human nature. The stronger you pushed our walls, the tighter we build our barricade.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Some other societies could answer to the rising social complexities with ambivalence between literal back-to-the-book approach, while superficially adapting themselves to be in the centre of the inflicted social changes. This is the most perplexing communities to face. We see no philosophical ground on both end of the story. Ambivalence at its finest.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>To illustrate, let’s imagine the following case: In modern times, when world civilisation had made way to diplomacy and multicultural cohabitation, it seems anachronistic to go to Friday prayer and listen to the sermon about heaven and hell, and whether it’s halal or not to kill your non-believer neighbour…. Unfortunately, 9 out of 10 sermon here, that’s what you’ll get. Are we still living in the age of war against the infidels?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>How could that be? I guess that’s what happened when you juxtapose modern context with ancient wisdom without having to go through the entire understanding process. The current mainstream Indonesian moslem society that I know around me, failed miserably in providing the Islam that I see fit: A faith of critical judgement, compassionate values, and contextual rules.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>Coping Mechanism</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I guess these reasons are the cause being a moslem in this country is hard enough, and it’s understandable why more and more young people tend to lose their faiths. More and more people  like me are questioning the true measure of well-functioning society. How can we not? We are so used to face a moral dilemma as follows:</p>
</div>
<div class="quoteblock">
<blockquote>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>To be a good citizen in my society, I should show myself practising good routines of my religion, I should go to Friday prayers, for instance.
In my friday prayers, I am told that it’s okay to hate your non-believers neighbour. Does that made me a good moslem? Does that make me a good individual in the face of society?</p>
</div>
</blockquote>
</div>
<div class="quoteblock">
<blockquote>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The people around me, tend to preach about sins and good deeds. Life and deeds are zero sum game, and God is an accountant…. Wait… What?!!</p>
</div>
</blockquote>
</div>
<div class="quoteblock">
<blockquote>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Is it really true, that showing that I’m good at MY religion DOES make me a good functioning citizen of my society? Does that make me a hypocrite, or does that make me presentable?</p>
</div>
</blockquote>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Young members of modern society could challenge these views in their daily basis. Their coping mechanism resort to their understanding of religion the way they see fit. This article, whether it’s true or not, relevant or not, is simply just a coping mechanism. And the debate that goes along with these kinds of expressions, are also coping mechanisms.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Furthermore, I don’t think people who announce that they’re starting to question their faiths should be addressed to, or considered a threat. We all know that these people are results of their own coping mechanism towards local interpretations of values, unfit social construct, multi-faceted exposures, and self expression… The problem lies more in the environmental aspect of the practised religion, not on the beholder of faith.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>Where now?</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Well, the dream to engage more people like me to be more spiritual and religious, is to put more sense on how religion itself is used to govern society.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>No, it’s not going to Friday prayers that will make you a good moslem. It’s not having to fast for 29 days that will make you a good moslem. It’s by understanding why such rules are born in its times, and understanding a holistic impact on our society that will make you a good moslem. It’s by embracing the critical, compassionate, and contextual aspect of the religion, then you could be a good moslem.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>It’s to have a firmer stand about why you’re doing the rituals to your faith. No, don’t say that because the book says so. Don’t say that I’ll go to hell if I don’t comply. We need more tangible experience regarding the way we do our faiths. Not just some blind propaganda and fear-induced repercussions….</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Some societies had succeed, but I guess the majority of people haven’t follow through…</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Where do you stand?</p>
</div>]]></description><link>http://gudhakesa.com/2017/08/13/On-faith-and-religion-in-local-context.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gudhakesa.com/2017/08/13/On-faith-and-religion-in-local-context.html</guid><category><![CDATA[words]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Mahendra Gudhakesa]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[On Life and Education]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>Hello Everyone.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Today is a fine day indeed. I stand here, feeling more than honored to be with you all. In midst of euphoria, joy, hope, and gladness, and also cluelessness and uncertainties, I am here to try to address some of the things I learned from life and my experience.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>As we all know, there is no one-grand-strategy when it comes to life. We realize that the success story in the past, won&#8217;t help much to navigate our future. We could still be hopeful, but we are at the very foundation, uncertain.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Let&#8217;s forget a little bit about uncertainties. Let&#8217;s enjoy this grandiose summer morning with laughter and hope. Let&#8217;s fill today with optimism and a laid-back fun. Here I stand with you people, on this particularly fine day, to talk to you about three most important lesson I had received throughout my life. About education, and about life. I am here, to talk to you about: Commencement, Misdirections, and Resolution.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>Commencement</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>You and me, we are one of the luckiest people on earth now. We live in a world where things had never been better. A little harder, yes, but never been better. The world as we know it has never been so optimistic and vibrant. We live now in time where opportunities and choices are so abundant, we have more of it than we have time.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Education, has been more relevant to people now. A lot of people have access to it, people are no longer afraid (or at least less afraid) to student loans or financing. We understand fully that education is more pivotal than ever. So we strive our society to have access to that.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Science has been more democratized now than previous years. And yet, we stand here on this event, as one of the luckiest person on earth, to have experience it all. Let us at first, be grateful of that fact, as we cherished our  drenched-in-agony years we had&#8230;&#8203;</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I graduated from university myself, around 30 years ago. I stand where you stand now, looking up to the world with anticipation and will as big as the world can offer me. There is no day like today, that speak to me as importantly as the day of commencement.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>What is the core idea of commencement? Commencement is the start of the story. The first step of a thousand miles journey. Commencement, is indeed, be the scariest part of life. Yet it is unarguably the most important life event we may have taken in every journey we step into. It is the time when unjustified innocence face its trial, aspirations are challenged, and decisions must be made. It is the day when faith and willpower start to play their role. And today, of course, could be one of those days for you.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I start my career after my university graduation, with a choice to make. And it was not an easy one. Two roads emerge in the woods, as Robert Frost would have phrased it. And I took the road less traveled, and that had made all the difference.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>It was full of regrets, victorious triumph, and celebrations. It doesn&#8217;t matter what the outcomes are. What mattered was, I commenced myself into that path. I survived.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>There is no recorded best practice to follow when it comes to life&#8217;s commencement day. There are wisdom spoken to us from many sources about how to deal with commencement. The only way to deal with commencement, is to really take that first step, in any directions you think is available at the moment.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Commencement day, for me, is a time of faith. It has no room for indecisiveness and worry. No matter how you view today, no matter how uncertain you are in your future. It is just as important to understand that today is also one of the most important days of your life.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>When you moved on from today, you are obliged to make bigger decisions for your life, and there is nothing better than that. Because life, is a series of commencement.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Constantly, try to do that leap of faith, hold true to the fact that to fall is the only way you will go. And you always have the chance to do so, beautifully. The point of commencement, is a reminder that life is full of leap-of-faiths. You jump again, after you survive another.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>Misdirections</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I remember myself, and lots of my peers when I graduate. We speak a lot about opportunities and chances that we can take. We talk a lot about hope and aspirations. We talk about the path we could now choose, thanks to the keys we obtained in classes and courses,</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I was wrong. I should have never thought of my previous years within these walls as a journey to obtain keys and access to the wider worlds.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>It took me years after to finally understand that what I was equipped with, are wrenches and bolts.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Education, knowledge, or a degree, are only tools. Hard-earned tools we obtained through discipline, papers, and deadlines. All that efforts we put to ourselves, endless sleepless nights, will not guarantee us to be master craftmans and creators. It is a mere training on to use those tools. A basic one.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>And on a day like today, when we finally obtain those tools, the world no longer care on what you have on your walls. The world care more about what you can create with those tools. In fact, the world only care about what you can create. They do not care much about the tools you now have, or how you obtained them</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>On this day, it is important that we constantly ask ourselves on what are the things we want to create to the world. What are the things matter to us the most? And how can we start building that thing?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>What then, are the things you could create with wrenches and bolts alone?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Maybe, we need hammers and nails too. And hammers and nails, are the things you obtain when you indulge on the things you love dwelling in.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Do not forget on the importance of hammer and nails. As it is also one of the things that will help you create things.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>To believe that education is the key for a better living, is a misdirection. It is merely an enlarged opportunity to create one.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>Resolution</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Van Gogh, would never be the way he is, if he only painted A Starry Night throughout his life. Just like Da Vinci, would never be known if his notebook only contains one invention.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>A baker, would not be called a baker if he baked only one batch of loaf. Just like any maker, would not be a maker if he make only one thing at a time.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>People could come up with many recipes on how to be good at something. Hard work, repetition, mastery, practice, discipline, and so on. It&#8217;s an exhaustive list of self-help words you might find in your local bookstore. Willpower? That would be a great buzzword too.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>But however you frame it, whatever word you choose to be the foundation of great achievements, for me is resolution. A resolution well defined, is when you put huge amount of intention, decision, and commitment to do something, to constantly do it, or to create, and to constantly create. It&#8217;s a form of mental determination to keep doing (or making) things you believe the world would need.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Keeping the spark of your creation alive, is just as important with the activity of creating itself.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I stand here, looking at you eager young minds, with high hopes that you are the future creator of a better world. I stand here hoping that you will take part in the most important part of our civilization. I hope you would never stop creating things you believe in. With all the tools you had received today, tomorrow, and the days beyond.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Remember, that you are the master of your crafts..</p>
</div>]]></description><link>http://gudhakesa.com/2017/06/11/an-imaginary-commencement-address.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gudhakesa.com/2017/06/11/an-imaginary-commencement-address.html</guid><category><![CDATA[words]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Mahendra Gudhakesa]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 11 Jun 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Life Lessons From Video Games]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>Many ’90s kids like us have experienced our own discomfort (if not hardship) dealing with video games. We remember the time we first got our hands on that small plastic controller of that 8-bit console. It was constant, near-impossible negotiations between us and our parents about how much time we should spend in front of the device.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Fast forward another 10 years, and I guarantee most of us still face the same problems. These sneaky habits we learned from avid video game use stuck with us while we were growing up. Little did our parents know playing these games could shape our lives in the most positive way imaginable. For me, it taught me a lot about life, and how to endure it.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I remember the times I played the crazily expansive MMORPG (Massive Multiplayer Online Role Playing Game) games. They stole most of my bedtime and studying time, and prevented me from doing my chores.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>From the hack and slash types like “Diablo,” “Titan Quest” and “Dungeon Siege,” to the massive, multiplayer type like “The Old Republic,” and “World of Warcraft,” you name it, I played it.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>These games hold a special place in my heart. I enjoyed the time spent skipping classes and being antisocial within the comfort of my bedroom playing these games. And I can say, after more than 10 years of experience, those days were worth it.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Here are five lessons I learned from playing video games all through childhood:</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>They taught me to be myself.</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>And being yourself DOES take effort. I am a late adopter of RPG games. I started playing them when most of my friends had made it halfway through the journey. When I started playing, all I did was copy whatever methods they had. If they said being a fire conjurer and warrior is the best thing to be, then so be it. What happened then? I sucked. Big time.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Eventually, I learned to carefully read character descriptions. I had to understand the best way to play, and the way I would like to play the battles and bosses. Something as simple as choosing a suitable character became an event because I had to take the time to really understand the way I played the games.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I had to understand how short-tempered I was to actually realize I’m not really the “support class” kind of person. I was more like a close encounter, melee, dual-wielding type of guy. By understanding that, I started a series of successful battles and fights. It took in-depth understanding of the way I react to the game before I could choose a suitable character/skill I wanted to use.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>This applies to life. It takes effort to measure yourself and know yourself. This is a fundamental skill we need to have to win the battle that is life. It’s OK to indulge ourselves in many skills and possibilities, but at the end of the day, you’ll be forced to choose one or two things you want to spend your life doing. Life itself is all about that journey of self-discovery.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>It took even more in-depth understanding to get used to the way I handle problems, and how I feel about facing adversity. We can’t go through life by copying other people’s coping mechanisms. It’s our job to pave our own path.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Self-discovery is the essential factor for us to recognize our full potential, our role in life. So, take your time.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>You may know how to get things done, but you’re never better than other people.</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>OK, we’ve successfully understood each our battle type. We know every measure and skill necessary to play the game our own way. But we can never say we’re better than other players.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>We can never say the Barbarian is better than the Paladin. We can never say the conqueror is better than the assassin, or the Jedi is better than the smuggler. We have to remember that our choices are made because it fits us. And at the end of the day, we need those other players in our party, too.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The same goes with life. We are wherever we are because we decided to be there; it fits us. It doesn’t necessarily go well with other people’s plans and ideas, but in the end, we’ll need them, too. We will never know what kind of dungeon raid we’ll get ourselves into in real life, and we don’t know what kind of surprises are waiting just around the corner.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>And in some aspects of life, collaboration with the people who are different than you will be the only way to overcome an obstacle.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>Life could always be harder.</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Hardship comes naturally, especially in video games. The only way you can say your game is making progress, is by realizing your quest is becoming a lot longer, more strenuous and a lot more difficult than when you started.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>That’s the whole point of playing the game in the first place. We want to progress, so we take on more advanced missions and quests, and we explore the map to have a better view of the world we live in.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>If your life isn’t getting any harder than it was yesterday, then there’s something’s not right. You should always be challenging yourself. We need to constantly explore new opportunities in order to broaden our horizons, to have a bigger “map.” It will give us a better understanding of what makes the world go round, and will help us make more sense of it all.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>Focus is key, but having a sidetracked life is not a sin.</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>It’s a necessity. The concept of “Main Quest” and “Side Quest” is quite common in MMORPG games. Main quests deal more with story line and class progression, while side quests act as extra missions with modest rewards. It seems like trivial tasks, but in the end, it’s worth enduring if you want to level up. Side quests prepare you for the face off with the main boss.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>We are raised to focus our lives more on main goals and achievements. Our main quest in life is to go to school, graduate, have a steady job, find your passion and so on. But in the end, we do know that in order for us to grow, to gain experience, it’s the small side quests that matter.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>It’s about the opportunity we take advantage of when we meet an old man walking down the street. It’s the damsel in distress we meet on the path we took back to your next quest. It’s the business opportunity handed over by a friend while we’re hanging out at the local bar. Give it a go, and it will help you later on your main quest.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>Life should be cherished.</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>At the end of the game, you realize why you played in the first place. We all crave adventure. We’re craving some action, and we’re hungry for exploration.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>We understand every failure is an opportunity to reformulate our strategy and upgrade our levels, and then we start again. Even if it took countless tries, we didn’t give up. We tried again and again until we earned that crown or legendary item.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Life is one epic MMORPG game. We’re required to measure ourselves, to decide our role, to select our skills, and develop them accordingly. We’re required to be in constant action, slashing enemies, overcoming adversities and defeating monsters beyond our wildest dreams. Our quest is to be, and to overcome. Our journey is to grow, and to level up. And in times of defeat, our job is to bounce back up and try again.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Life is one hell of a game, and it’s one you should be excited about. And at the end, you’ll feel all the troubles you face are worth the time and effort. The journey is worth the fun. And at the end of the journey, you’ll be proud to have lived life to the fullest.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Game on.</p>
</div>]]></description><link>http://gudhakesa.com/2017/02/25/Life-Lessons-From-Video-Games.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gudhakesa.com/2017/02/25/Life-Lessons-From-Video-Games.html</guid><category><![CDATA[words]]></category><category><![CDATA[ millennials]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Mahendra Gudhakesa]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 25 Feb 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[UX and LIterature]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="sect2">
<h3 id="_a_little_back_story">A little back story</h3>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Before I become a practitioner inside the UX field, I was previously not a person in design, software, tech, tech-startup, or anything that are close to the term. The term “UX Research” or “UX Design”, as much as they become the buzzword of the year, didn’t come to my attention until the last 12 months. I have spent my previous professional career working in qualitative research, doing research in many field like social research, cultural studies, and more specifically: developing marketing efforts for brands and companies in order to connect better with their consumers. It’s easy to find my name among the people working in consumer goods companies or business consultants.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Finally, by jumping in to work at a UX / CX Design firm, opened my journey towards understanding more about the world of UX, and also became the first turning point for me to get hands-on to UX processes.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Surprisingly, many of the discipline and efforts in doing UX research have many similarities with my previous experiences. Much of the UX discipline cross many of the qualitative research discipline I’ve learned. We shared similar way of thinking and mindset when trying to understand why people behave like they do, and we also put the same importance of that knowledge.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="sect2">
<h3 id="_ux_the_general_idea">UX: The General Idea</h3>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>To me, the main idea of UX efforts are about integrating products (or services, or technology) into our day of life. UX can be seen as an effort to streamline a product’s disruption in entering the way we do our daily lives. Of course this term is a very broad definition, but let’s start from there.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The discipline of UX, in my opinion, begins at the question of “how will a product integrate with our daily conducts? How will it change the the way we do things before?”. The key main role of the product here is to transform our habit, our conduct, and the way we do our usual tasks, no matter how small.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Our role as UX designers or researchers in the business value chain, then, is to position that particular product as our client. And like any client, they have their own goal for us to tackle. It is within our duty to make sure that the product’s disruption in our daily lives, are as smooth as possible.</p>
</div>
<div class="quoteblock">
<blockquote>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><em>UX designers: We&#8217;re the gatekeepers of innovation and disruption.</em></p>
</div>
</blockquote>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>This approach sounds very similar in my previous line of work as a market researcher and brand builder. It is also within a market researcher’s duty to make sure that the brand they are working on can disrupt people’s habit and behavior, or to make sure that brands can understand its target consumers precisely so that they can really give the consumers a meaningful product and services.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>In essence, to establish a meaningful experience for target consumers / users / customers through products and services, are quintessential works to both UX researcher and market researcher. If brand builders are the gatekeepers of stories, consumption, and habit, then UX designers have the same responsibility: to be the gatekeepers of product innovation and disruption.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="sect2">
<h3 id="_the_common_question_for_empathy">The common question for empathy</h3>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>In doing UX or research approach, empathy to the target user is essential. And to achieve empath, we have to ask ourselves the most basic question: <strong>“what is it like to be them?”</strong>. Our task as researchers (or designers) eventually is to unearth a worldview in which our users / consumers live in.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Not only unearthing those worldviews, we are also obliged to live in them, understanding their way of thinking, what motivates them, how they live their lives, and eventually, how they are going to react when exposed to our products or services? We are required to be able to “read” people and their genuine reaction towards whatever offer we’re about to make for them.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Then, the question I’m often asked, what tools could be helpful for a UX researcher to have empathy? For me, a good appreciation of literature helps a lot…</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="sect2">
<h3 id="_the_importance_of_steinbeck_and_orwell_in_building_empathy">The importance of Steinbeck and Orwell in building empathy</h3>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>There is no more robust tool for a UX researcher to understand users other than observation and storytelling.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The essence of being ourselves, our identities, or constellation of values are all embedded in, well, stories. The way we share our worldviews with the world, the way we share our political beliefs, our arguments, our experiences, are all in the form of stories. Stories as one of the main observation points for qualitative researchers, doesn’t only speak on individual levels, but also at cultural levels. The way societies and civilizations progress are by series of events happening, and retold in stories.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Unearthing stories surrounding the lives of the user comes to be a very important part of doing UX work. It is by making them to tell us their stories, we will be able to dive deep into their beliefs, values, and worldview. To position ourselves as UX researcher / designer, is like positioning ourselves like a documentary maker, a filmmaker, or a writer.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Think of John Steinbeck in “Of Mice and Men”. Think of how Steinbeck really put up a good narrative in helping us understand the lives and worries of plantation workers, farmers, or ranch workers. Or the best example that I can think of is George Orwell’s flawless observation and narrative in “Down and Out in Paris &amp; London”. Orwell orchestrated a good example of observation and storytelling. He had succeeded in empathizing with waiters and chefs in a Parisian restaurants (or a beggar in London), understanding their motives, worries, and view of life, and retold that story and observation in impeccable narrative. What helped him doing so is the fact that he himself dived deep into the lives of those people (although unwillingly), and opened his eyes into the untold details of the people around him.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>That’s why I believe that to be a good UX researcher / designer is for us to walk the Orwellian path of observation and storytelling. When we can dedicate our efforts truthfully, genuinely, in understanding our target users, we will be able to ask the right question, select the proper method, and also conduct it more effortlessly.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The question that we can ask ourselves, UX researchers / designers, is: Can we be the next Orwell or Steinbeck?</p>
</div>
</div>]]></description><link>http://gudhakesa.com/2017/01/16/an-outsiders-perspective-of-UX-research-and-design.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gudhakesa.com/2017/01/16/an-outsiders-perspective-of-UX-research-and-design.html</guid><category><![CDATA[words]]></category><category><![CDATA[ research]]></category><category><![CDATA[ UX]]></category><category><![CDATA[ qualitative]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Mahendra Gudhakesa]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[The dream and the celebration of being young]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div id="preamble">
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="quoteblock">
<blockquote>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Forever is not enough.
Nothing can tear as apart.
To be at your side (whenever, wherever).
To be in your heart (whenever, wherever).</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>~"Destiny", By Homogenic</strong></p>
</div>
</blockquote>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I would like to dedicate this post to generation Z kids, whose coming of age are now spent in schools and universities. You&#8217;re the real representation of the young up to this day, and there&#8217;s nothing more I would like to say to you other than some thought-evoking piece, and means for self reflection. I believe adolescence years, or university years are the most pivotal moment someone could experience. I&#8217;ve passed that moment long ago, but the memory remains.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>When we&#8217;re young enough to escape the dread of adulthood, but old enough to practice responsibilities and exercise freedom, there is one universal longing that each of us may face. This universal longing, revealed to me through a dream, is what I am going to talk about in these threaded letters&#8230;&#8203;</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="sect1">
<h2 id="_the_dream">The dream</h2>
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="paragraph">
<p>It was one autumn afternoon. I was just about to leave the last class of the semester. I grab my pullover jacket as I walked outside the university building. The wind was pretty much chilly, but a comfortable chill. With occasional gust rushing down my face, I could say that it is a lovely afternoon somehow. The campus was just finishing its last day of semester. The student bodies and fraternity houses are arranging a communal party in celebration of the end of semester. Though the ambience of the scene was pretty laid back, I can sense the exhilaration and relief in the people around me. They were smiling more, laughing more, and I can&#8217;t help but to share the same spark of joy.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>A friend (whom I&#8217;ve never saw in real life) walked towards me, asking "are you going to the concert tonight?".
"Yeah sure.", I replied.  We walked together around the campus complex, talking about the frolic we encounter throughout the semester. The small talks we made assured me that me and him are long-time pals. We talked a lot about the things I never remember having in  real life. But nevertheless, it was a very enjoyable talk.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>It was a peculiar setting, seeing the people present at the dream. Much of the people I&#8217;ve met and talked to are the people I did not meet until later in my professional years after graduating. There&#8217;s this guy whom I haven&#8217;t seen since I graduated in real life. There&#8217;s also my ex-coworker who did not attend the same university as I do. There&#8217;s also an old high school friend I never talk to. There&#8217;s my coach in the university marching band, planning to get drunk in the library&#8217;s basement with his close friend. Why am I seeing them in this dream? Attending the same university and sharing the same scene of youth utopia, I don&#8217;t know for sure. They&#8217;re simply there.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The scene, the people, keep changing throughout the day. From a laid-back party scene iin one of the school cafetaria, a concert performed by Homogenic, up until it was a little bit past midnight. We were planning to go back home from our evening walks. So I said goodbye to everyone I met along the way. It was at this moment I opened my eyes and realized that it was a dream. A vivid and strange one indeed.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<div class="sect1">
<h2 id="_the_train_of_thought_that_follows">The train of thought that follows</h2>
<div class="sectionbody">
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I&#8217;m no psychoanalyst. I don&#8217;t do well in interpreting dreams and its meanings, but I do understand that dreams serve as fragments of abstract images from our previous experiences. It also reveals to us our deepest longings. I contemplated deeply, trying to make sense of what I just saw.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I&#8217;m not good at making an accurate sense of that dream, but some things are definitely clear to me. First, I miss my adolescence years. It&#8217;s a time of opportunities and experimentations. It&#8217;s a time of deep learning in which I regretted skipping some opportunities of taking up life&#8217;s lesson. And secondly, it reveals to me that if I am ever going to repeat that phase of my life, I would rather spend it with the friends I make today. Not the friends that I made back then. Clearly, I realized that there are people whom I currently wish I grew up together with.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>My dream about the adolescence years, revealed to me my inner longing of wanting to experience once again, the togetherness of making a life-shaping journey, a longing for making a long-term connection shaped by common experience and camaraderie with the people who matters most to me today.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>These are good insights for me. It reminds me of the things that define our youth. I believe the longing we experience when we were young, revealed to me in a dream, are a universal longing present in all of us.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I tried to pin down the main things we, and every young people around us long for. And I could come up with a few things. And these things, I believe, are the things that every young people should be able to do.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>If you&#8217;re currently young enough to relate to my words, I would recommend you live your life doing these things. It&#8217;s for your own good.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>Exploring curiosities</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Exploring curiosities are one of the main perks of youth. It&#8217;s a chance for you to wonder and wander. To ask questions, to be inquisitive, and be goddamn curious about anything. It&#8217;s a natural calling for young people, and should be taken seriously. If some things are able to get you wondering, then it&#8217;s worth to think about seriously. In the end, what is youth if it&#8217;s not a constant child-like wonder?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I always believe that adolescence should serve as your second childhood. It&#8217;s the peak time of psychological development, and emotional intelligence. Back when you were five, you learn how to move that little hands of yours, how to walk and move efficiently, how to operate a computer, and so on. But when you&#8217;re in adolescence, it&#8217;s when you learn to feel and to think. You will experience the yearning for philosophy and reason. And there is no excuse in not exercising those things. Be curious, be curious.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>Making small experimentations</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Experiment on all things. Try things. Experience new stuff! Experience failure! Experience heartbreak! Try photography! Learn to do yo-yo tricks! Try a new romance! Just try! You will never find better timing to try all of these stuff. It&#8217;s a time for you to challenge yourself fairly and openly, because nobody gives a damn on what you can do at the first place. If you think it&#8217;s doable, then you should probably try it.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The value of making small experimentations goes a long way in life. Nobody regret the things they did more than they regret the things they didn&#8217;t do. Making small experimentations are like investing your time, resources, thoughts, and experiences on things that may come up later in life.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>Have small celebrations. In fact, celebrate everything</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I mean it. Celebrate everything. You passed that test? Celebrate it! Grab some beer and go out with friends. You finally get that pretty girl&#8217;s number in physics class? Celebrate it. For every milestone you set for your small life experiments, celebrate it. Celebrate both success and failures. Have fun.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I think hollywood movies get it right when it comes to college or university life. Its depiction of constant partying and having fun are indeed essential. We just need to frame it on a more productive terms. To celebrate everything, means to accept everything life had thrown at you. There is no better times to learn other than your college life. Trust me.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>Learn to be there for others, in times of need</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>You are not alone. You&#8217;re part of a communal growing-up rites of passage with the people around you. You share the same responsibility on making those small life-experiments. You are the only people accessible to your friends when they want to talk about their curiosities. You are the one they would turn to in moments of small celebrations. In essence, the things you want to do in your youth, you will never experience it alone. You will share that journey with your red-haired flat-mate, you&#8217;ll share that with that dude who helped you ace mechatronics.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>And the least you can do is simply by being there for other people. It&#8217;s important for you to understand that each and everyone around you now are longing to do all of those things I wrote. It&#8217;s indeed a shared experience, and trust me when I say that the kind of people you associate yourself at this particular time, in your youth, will determine the kind of people you become.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>]]></description><link>http://gudhakesa.com/2017/01/12/Letter-to-generation-Z.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gudhakesa.com/2017/01/12/Letter-to-generation-Z.html</guid><category><![CDATA[words]]></category><category><![CDATA[ millennials]]></category><category><![CDATA[ generation Z]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Mahendra Gudhakesa]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Allure of The Corporate Career Path]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>I graduated university in July 2011. I obtained my bachelor degree from one of the most notable public university in the country. Although there are some friends who chose to go through the traditional career path like they were prepared for, at that time I remember what trend is going on among us fresh graduates. That is the allure of starting your own company. And long story short, that’s what I did.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Right after graduating, I started a small branding &amp; design firm based in Jakarta with a couple of friends. The time was good back then, and we were proud. We might not have much money to make at first, but we do appreciate the flexibility and versatility on the way we work. We hang out with clients, spend time more with them as they were our friends and partners. And to my generation, that is exactly what matters most when you start out into the professional world. The potential for meaningful connections and the meaningful work we could do is always right under our noses.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I never regretted this decision in my life. I continue life, treat it as series of open doors and opportunities, and still believing that the future of young people around me will be like what I perceived it to be in 2011. I believe that more and more people in the upcoming future, will follow the path I’ve chosen.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Five years straight to 2016, I really thought the world had progressed the way I thought it would be. I thought that there will be more and more people who are like me when they graduate, wanting to make more business out of their interests and passion. That turned out to be false.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>The Supply Had Not Met The Demand</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Some time ago, I met a long-time friend of mine, an HR specialist working in the big corporate world. We talked a lot about the current youth reality, and what she said to me is rather surprising. At least more than 80% of fresh graduates she met between the year 2015 and 2016, are all still interested to get into the corporate world. So, the trend isn’t changing as much as I thought it would be in 2011.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>That fact alone strikes me as unusual. While in my experience working closely with HR departments from big companies, I often heard they were having difficulties in recruiting the right people for their organisations. But the reality among the fresh grads are: more than 80% of them actually want to get into the corporate world. We got one side complaining about not able to find the right people for their job. But the other side, the fresh grads side, hundreds of thousands of people each year are ready to kill for a decent position in those organisation.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>So I asked her further about her experience working in her company. How do the young people perform? The pain in the ass for her is having to look at the employee turnover report that reached 65% a year.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>So I get it. Majority of fresh-grads (80%) wants to work in big corporations after they graduate. From all that made it through, 65% of them probably quit their first job in the first year.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p> — -</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I’m curious and a little bit perplexed. So I decided to dive deeper into this reality. I would like to know what is millennials’ aspiration when it comes to work. Or to be more specific, what are the things they aspire to do after graduating?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Yes, I can’t deny it, although the popular media now are heading to the utopia of entrepreneurship, craftmanship, and pursuing your interest, the majority of university students we met still aspire in getting into the corporate world.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The reason behind it was pretty much straightforward, and not that different from what my parents had taught me. The promise of a fix income in midst of uncertain economy, or the potential to be exposed in numerous job description, and work location. It’s well understood that for these millennials, the main allure of the big corporate world for them, mostly come from Management Trainee programs, ODPs, and other programs alike.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Of course, I am not against them on choosing such path for their lives. I realized I might have chosen a stray path against the mainstream choice back when I was graduating. But that doesn’t mean the mainstream is wrong.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>My attention shifted to the corporate reality. Companies that I have worked with often nag about keeping millennials engaged and motivated in the workplace. One of the most common hypotheses they have is, the failure of keeping them engaged and motivated often end up in high employee turnovers.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Is it really the corporations fault? On not having able to engage with millennials? I hardly think so. The millennials we talked to also mentioned that, although they want to dive deep into the corporate world, it’s not their main goal at the first place. The main goal in the end is having their own businesses and crafts. The function of getting into the corporate world serves solely as a jump-start for their goal.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>So, the reality of fresh graduates turns out to progress the way I see it, just not as straightforward as I thought it would be.
And I think the main problem is, big corporations simply try to motivate and engage millennials in ways that they think might have worked for people in the previous generations. While we, millennials, are self aware enough to know that the kind of motivation, benefit, and engagement that the companies give us, aren’t worth the long run. It doesn’t help us in achieving our dreams in making businesses, creations, or crafts.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>But eventually, I would not say that the time-served by millennials in the corporate world is a waste of time for us. Millennials know it well, that the experience gained in doing 9-to-5 services in a cubicle is a well-needed discipline in building our future creations. What is asked often by millennials like me, in the end, is just how long do I need to do a 9-to-5 service? Is it a year? 2 years? Or maybe just enough to survive probation?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The challenge now is for big corporations to rethink their HR policy and work environment to enable more meaningful collaboration with millennials, each with their own dreams and aspirations. At first, I think it’s crucial for companies to acknowledge first, that millennials have deeper agenda than serving a 9-to-5 in cubicles while getting paid to do so.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>In my utopian professional world, I want to imagine a work environment where there is common respect and understanding between a millennial and his/her employer about the dreams both want to achieve (this is probably why many millennials get the allure of startups, but that’s for another story). The failure of corporate engagements at the moments because they think of an ideal environment is for someone to dedicate their time fully to the organization’s goals alone. The room for inter-organization collaboration, for instance, haven’t really been the topic in the corporate world, let alone self-fulfilment. This is not the way millennials really think about their future.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>This is why I think it’s crucial for corporations and millennials to have a more meaningful dialogues. I still believe there are ways to bridge the gaps, and I think it’s necessary that we start thinking on the way how. Because in the end, it’s for the sake of our own economy.</p>
</div>]]></description><link>http://gudhakesa.com/2016/11/10/On-choosing-careers.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gudhakesa.com/2016/11/10/On-choosing-careers.html</guid><category><![CDATA[words]]></category><category><![CDATA[ millennials]]></category><category><![CDATA[ work]]></category><category><![CDATA[ entrepreneurship]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Mahendra Gudhakesa]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 10 Nov 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Why making businesses should be millennials' cultural identity]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>I believe we had shifted our way of life, especially about ideals on making a living, a little too far-flung from what our parents’ had taught us. We&#8217;re the witness of student debt problems, unemployment, or even capitalism fallacy. We’re the first generation in the last decades who started thinking about skipping university and living life.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>We emphasize more on to express our own unique individuality, and we seek out for more serendipity. We’re the first horizontal-minded generation, as we shaped the sharing economy. Our serendipitous, horizontal-life had been our cultural identity, and I think it’s time to make the best of it. How are we going to do that? I think we should make more businesses.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Millennials are the generation that went beyond the traditional sense of business. Businesses for us is more than just transfer of values, resources, supply chains, or profits. We think of business as one of the truest form of civilisation advancement. In philosophy, making businesses could be the noblest form of profession because it’s the only profession that tends to create platform, or medium where expertise, character, and networks grow. Enterpreneurism are now embedded in our dreams and life goals.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Making businesses means having that caregiving hands that groom magic out of series of value exchange between one party and another. In short, history had proven that businesses are one of the things that make the world go round. And guess what? Aren’t we in more advantageous position to do so at the moment?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Entrepreneurship, or making businesses is all about looking for that opportunity: a gap, somewhere inside this world’s value chain that you can tap into, create benefits, and deliver better results to the end of the line. It’s all about establishing that platform inside the chain that you can work over and over again, plant the seed of innovation, and reap the fruits of your labour.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Entrepreneurship itself had been a very alluring topic amongst our generation. Not because we’re naturally more savvy businessmen compared to our parents, and nor because we’re simply bored  and unmotivated to work somewhere in some established enterprises. The key difference in our generation is we put more emphasis on our own self expression or self enjoyment. We put value on the things we really, really love doing. This is really something that is truly millennial.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>We express our unique individuality. We tend to be more inquisitive too in pursuing things of our interest. We study deeply the things that excite us, we enjoy ourselves so much doing those things,  we indulge in creating something out of it, and we tell others about it. We learn, we enjoy, we create, and we share. But we don’t want to stop there. The real appealing thing comes to us when we do more than just “tell others about it”. Then it is natural for us to think about monetizing what we do.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>The Passion-Driven Work as Millennials' Strength</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The idea of having work that are integrated or congruent with our object of passion is a relatively novel idea. This idea about work doesn&#8217;t show up until the late 20th century, but rather made by people in the last decade. The growth of global economy had given us more opportunity, especially the young people, to be more expressive and able to indulge more with variety of interest and activities. Our wide range of interests and activities actually had given us possibilities which our previous generations didn’t really have.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Our devotion &amp; inquisitiveness to our interests could be the answer to the hardest step of making a business: identifying that opportunity, or to point that gap somewhere inside the world’s value chain. When we decide to cash in on our passions, we put the responsibility to study deep about it, and putting efforts to make life a little better. In short, we would want to try making a more seamless value chain out of the things we love doing.  There’s nothing more emotionally-engaging than making our own living through the things we enjoy, right?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>What’s more interesting about making business from the thing we enjoy most is, we’re actually re-shaping common knowledge about how businesses should be done. Business school class, and self-help books often taught us about the three stages of making businesses work: It’s all about making the right amount of profit, seek growth, and maintain sustainability. But the way we’re doing it, we tend to do it backwards. Our paradigm to make our passion-driven businesses work is: We want to make it sustainable first (because we want to do what we love as long as possible), we then seek growth (because we like it when more people joins in, and that’s why we often hear about startups “scaling up”), and then we seek out ways to maximise our profits.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>When we make business out of our passions, we are able to do the whole thing a little differently than old businesses' wisdoms. Suddenly, what we see in the business world are people who started to see things emerging such as crowdfunding, kickstarter campaigns, and products with personalities. And it turns out, this new paradigm in making businesses work had made the world a lot better than we could ever imagine. Harvard Business Review, or The Economist had written about these kinds of emerging business model and startups more prominently than we could find in the last 10 years.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>The Imagined Future for Millennials' Business</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Self expression is the main drive for us to create something, that’s why we’re the generation of creation. Judging from this point of view, I think making business is one of the ways we can make a dent in the universe. And we should always remember the fact that we’re all naturals in it. It’s within our responsibilities.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Because we know it all too well about living as millennials, we understand each of our fellow millennial&#8217;s struggle in making this happen. That&#8217;s why we&#8217;re more open for collaboration. We realized that the internet had given us democratized knowledge. We seek truthfulness in every event or stories (including marketing campaigns you throw at us). And we&#8217;re not going to be interested about the things you sell as easily as the previous generations. We&#8217;re more excited to hear why are you doing things, or selling things the way you are now. If you get our attention, we&#8217;d like to collaborate with you.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Advancement of civilisation had actually shaped us to the era where each and every one of us are like artisans and creators. We focus on our own selves, we self-reflect, we indulge in our interest, and we’re in charge of the world’s future economy. And by the power vested in us through social media, and global connectIvity, we&#8217;re ready to take on the world economy by storm. I believe each of us are starting to shape their story at the moment. Most of us already figure out the thing they love doing, and we&#8217;re going to make it big. Further than that, we&#8217;re ready to make it personal. So that’s why, making business out of passion should be the biggest consequence of our generations’ cultural Identity.</p>
</div>]]></description><link>http://gudhakesa.com/2016/10/18/Making-Businesses.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gudhakesa.com/2016/10/18/Making-Businesses.html</guid><category><![CDATA[words]]></category><category><![CDATA[ millennials]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Mahendra Gudhakesa]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Horizontal Career Path: A Discipline of Flexibility and Adaptability In The Modern World]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>Switching job is never easy. When you dedicate yourself climbing some corporate ladder, holding an establishsed professional position doing certain things, it takes certain degree of habit and experience. Switching out to other job is understandable a nuisance. The idea of having to adapt to new environment, new working habit, new people, and new responsibilities, could be one of many sources of anxiety towards our work.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>There are also specific fears associated with having to switch jobs. We all wanted our next job to be better compared with our previous ones. Whether it’s better benefits, better flexibility, better teams, or for many, what’s often considered is whether it has better pay.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Being in the late 20s, I have witnessed lots of people around me telling stories about them wanting to go out of their current job. Most of them feel unfulfilled, or unhappy with their current career. Being a millennial in spirit, I often say to them, “well, why don’t you? Just quit, resign, or whatever, find something else you’d like to do in life. I believe that the world still have a lot to offer you.. “</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>It turns out, most friends and colleagues often found my statement to be hard to swallow. There are always a glimpse of confusion, or rejection towards the idea I threw at them.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>“It’s not that easy… “ Some say to me.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I’m curious on how it’s not that easy. Very carefully they elaborate further on why. It turns out, some of my friends (who now had made it into the mid-management in some big corporations) find it hard to find a replacement job which offers the same kind of responsibility (or more), but with better pay. Salary or pay seem to be one of the main consideration to switch job. Even when one is unhappy with their current work, having the prospect of having a job with lower pay often considered not the way to go.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I get it, finding a company that could give you better pay, is indeed hard. Especially if you had made it to obtain an 8 figure IDR a month from a mid-management position. And the reality of the specific industry also play a role. If you’re a mid-management in an EPC or construction firm in Indonesia, good luck finding good opportunity for a better position WITH better pay. The whole industry landscape had saturated itself up to a point that career progression often means a considerable dead-end.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>So then I say, “why don’t you switch companies? Or industries?”. I found that my last statement is even harder to swallow among them.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The main source of anxiety towards switching jobs or careers, often stem from the fear of starting over from the bottom of the ladder again. Starting over from the bottom ALWAYS means having less paycheck. And the problem with having lesser paycheck is that most people don’t feel like they’re “progressing”, or in control of their life “progress”. Having to start over, is considered a setback.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Well, this idea is what I’d like to challenge.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>When I graduated, I was definitely starting over. I don’t directly go to EPC or O&amp;G companies to exercise my university expertise. In fact I decided to jump abroad into the marketing and design field. It was definitely hard at first. There are lots of new stuff I had to get accustomed to. There are lots of industry know-how I had to catch up. There are lots of details I need to re-learn.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Halfway to the top, I decided to make another shift to the research industry. And this time, I also had to re-learn all the know-how. And the pay? I receive lower amount compared to my previous job.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Then I move again to another startup company, still doing research stuff. I receive lower take-home-pay per month again. But the opportunity is huge. There are more potential exposure to clients and other small businesses, There are more things to do other than just doing research per-se. And a couple of years later. I ended up working with startups, ecosystem builders, photography schools, and many other things.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I often ask back to my friends and colleagues. Judging by my experience, was I progressing? Was receiving lower salary in each job-change means that I was progressing backwards? Comparing my friends stories with mine, I often ask myself, what is progress anyway?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Contrary to what my friends think, the way I see progress isn’t about the rising amount of a monthly salary. Progress, for me is about diversification of my skills and my work portfolio. It’s more about the expanding networks of people you’ve worked with, or the kind of activities you do differently in each job-change. Progress doesn’t always have to go in a vertical direction. Progress could go sideways, or horizontally.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>And believe me. The more you expand your ways horizontally, it comes easier and easier each time you do it. And what I came to realise later from my experience, that this encounter, is what I call the reduction of transaction cost.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Transaction cost is an intangible cost experienced when you were starting things over, or building back from scratch. Transaction cost occur alongside the hardship of starting anew, on re-learning new things, acquiring new knowledge, and working with new people.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The more I went expanding my skills and horizon, the less the transaction cost in my next job becomes. And I guess, this concept is kind of overlooked by people in mid or late 20s like my friends. It’s such a pity because often life give us many chances and opportunities, many open doors. And as the world is changing, our ability to adapt is more tested than before.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Once again, I am not against corporate careers and stuff. But I believe that one of the survival skill in the modern world is having to adapt quicker to modernity. And when we talk about progress, beside thinking about careers and paycheck-progression, it’s worth looking at progress from the point of view of investing on our flexibility across careers, and reducing transaction costs.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>After all, doesn’t old wisdom always say to us: “Don’t put all your luck in one basket?”</p>
</div>]]></description><link>http://gudhakesa.com/2016/10/18/A-Horizontal-Career-Path.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gudhakesa.com/2016/10/18/A-Horizontal-Career-Path.html</guid><category><![CDATA[words]]></category><category><![CDATA[ career]]></category><category><![CDATA[ work]]></category><category><![CDATA[ millennials]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Mahendra Gudhakesa]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 18 Oct 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Narrative Approach in Qualitative]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>One of the questions frequently asked by friends and colleagues about my work is always about what is it that I actually do. I often say to them that qualitative research (be it in marketing, design, or UX) is about understanding human experiences, and understanding the objects or things related to building human experience.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Qualitative research, as a tool for developing marketing / design strategies aren&#8217;t a new thing. It&#8217;s been done since the mid 20th century by advertising agencies, consumer goods manufacturer, or service providers. And understanding the approach of qualitative, in my opinion, could be the best thing to help you develop your business, especially if your business deal a lot with the everyday consumers.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Business owners often ask me for quick advice on how to make products deliver the best human experience. And for me, one of the interesting tools we can apply is the power of narrative or storytelling.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Basically, we all have stories to tell. We buy things, we use things, we consume things like snacks and ice cream because we want to have an experience. Experience itself is a very broad term. It doesn&#8217;t always talk about the good taste of the food you eat, it doesn&#8217;t talk about the good texture, it doesn&#8217;t talk about how good looking a fashion item you buy, and so on. Experiences are mostly about what kind of stories you want to feel for yourself while using or consuming a product. This is when narrative approach can be found useful.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Still confused? I&#8217;ll give you some examples then. I&#8217;ll tell you a story on how I approach or dissect human experiences. This time, I&#8217;ll talk about  experiences on snack consumption.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>So, let&#8217;s talk about a hypothetical consumer named Bob. Bob likes to eat potato chips. And me, as a qualitative researcher, or maybe people from frito-lay wants to understand more on why bob likes potato chips. It&#8217;s often not enough to ask Bob about why does he like potato chips. A rationalized answer is the only think we probably get from Bob if we ask him that way. The right way to ask is actually "What is the significance of potato chips in Bob&#8217;s life / daily routines / experience?".</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>This approach is very important when qualitative researchers are faced with a consumer reality. When we are asked, why do people consume the things they consume, it will take us deeper than having to ask Bob, why does he consume potato chips, for instance.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The best way to deal with this problem is to dive deep into Bob&#8217;s narratives. Narratives is an approach in which we believe that people always have a goal / a  theme in consuming something. Take a look at this childishly-drawn sets of boxes below:</p>
</div>
<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="http://gudhakesa.com/images/qual/connar.PNG" alt="connar.PNG">
</div>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>These are the things we should figure out every time we try to understand why Bob likes potato chips. We could start our journey by putting our attention to the green box (Settings / time / occasions / scenes). We could start asking Bob, on what occasions does he usually eat potato chips? Let&#8217;s list down Bob&#8217;s possible answer and review later.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Then we can move to the blue box (audiences). Who are there with him when he eats potato chips? On the grey box, we&#8217;ll ask bob, what would he feel if on that certain occasion with friends (or alone), he&#8217;s out of potato chips? What is the function of that particular potato chips ON that setting?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Then, let&#8217;s move backwards to the Yellow box (Product role / attributes). We could now ask Bob, what is it about the potato chips that you enjoy, ON THAT CERTAIN OCCASION? Now, when we&#8217;re assessing this yellow box, context is important. Isolate Bob&#8217;s potato-chips-occasion, and explore more on that context. If bob like to eat potato chips while watching the NFL night with friends, what is the allure of a bowl of potato chips? I mean, Why not ice cream instead on NFL nights?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Finally, to get to the red box, we can construct a comprehensive story on what role do potato chips play in bob&#8217;s routine. And what are the feelings Bob want to attain in the companion of Frito-lay&#8217;s potato chips? Constant observing and asking about potato chips with the narrative approach could give us a holistic view, of the significance of potato chips in Bob&#8217;s life. In short, we could now understand deeply on the role of potato chips in building the experience Bob wanted. I illustrated the results below:</p>
</div>
<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="http://gudhakesa.com/images/qual/connar2.PNG" alt="connar2.PNG">
</div>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Applied to other product categories, or services, this approach is useful to understand reasons on why people consumes the thing they consume. It&#8217;s also a way to understand why people behave like they do. This is a very simple explanation I often give to people around me about what does a qualitative researcher does, in context of design, UX, or even marketing.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I believe that this approach is not exclusively a qual researcher&#8217;s to own. Laypeople could also adopt this approach in building experiences they desire. To make full use of the narrative approach, there are a few things that a people have to keep in mind.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>First, let go of all judgement and bias</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Well, in order to be successful in dissecting somebody&#8217;s subjective experience is to understand that they are NOT you. They experience, perceive, and make sense of the world (and things) differently than your own. What is logical for you in making a decision, could possibly not be a logical decision at all for other people. This is very important to keep in mind before you start your observation and analysis.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>If you&#8217;re a product developer, understand that there are ways that people will use your product, and it could be a whole lot different than the first time you designed the product for. if you&#8217;re a chef or a cook, understand that not everybody have the same approach to taste and textures the way you have been educated. Understanding this, will be the first step on creating the most meaningful experience for your customers.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>Secondly, don&#8217;t take your consumers answers in face value</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Consumers don&#8217;t say what they mean, and they don&#8217;t mean what they say. They don&#8217;t think deep enough when asked about why they like to consume / buy things. So keep challenging them. Ask them further. Throw them additional "why", confirm, and reconfirm. Be prepared that whatever they say might only applicable in certain settings, or conditions. Be open, and explore deeper into their experience. You&#8217;ll unlock things you could probably never knew existed.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>Lastly, Observe! Observe! Observe!</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Words can mislead. Answers may lie. But the power of observation goes way beyond. Observe deeper on the way your customers deal with things, or deal with his / her world. Be sensitive to notice the things they do that you don&#8217;t normally do, or vice versa. Be in the present, and keep your eyes open for habits or actions previously unknown to you. You will be able to understand his / her experience a little better.</p>
</div>]]></description><link>http://gudhakesa.com/2016/10/07/understanding-experience-in-everyday-life.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gudhakesa.com/2016/10/07/understanding-experience-in-everyday-life.html</guid><category><![CDATA[words]]></category><category><![CDATA[ qualitative]]></category><category><![CDATA[ research]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Mahendra Gudhakesa]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[On Finding Your Writing Voice]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>Writing now has become an unfashionable craft. In midst of vlogs and podcasts, the art of making a point through threaded letters and well-crafted diction is diminishing. At least that’s the way I see it.
We live in times when we’re obsessed to get our points across to our audiences as fast as possible. Our point of view should be conversational, and as succinct as a 30-seconds pitch.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>While there’s nothing wrong with it, I still long for a writing culture in which it emphasize more on the power of words. To write is to impose tone and manner without the help of facial expression and audible emphasis. This is the craft I’d like to submit my devotion to at the moment.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I am always drawn to books and ideas. From classical writers to contemporary philosophy. Though letters, words, and writings will never cease to exist in our world, it is important for us to give more attention and discipline to it.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>One of the hardest thing in doing so, is to find your own voice. A constant, unchanging point of view, tone, manner, that could narrate a blank sheet of paper, or a blank white LCD screen. Finding your own voice could be a never-ending journey. It may take a lifetime. But I’d like to share some quick tips on how to find your own voice, and start your journey to the craft of writing.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>Write more, write often</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The most important thing for me to start this journey, is to write more and write often. Writing is not an overnight mastery. It took many hours, days, or years of constant dialogue with your inner self. Writing is not a virtue, it’s merely a habit.
There are no better advice I could share to people wanting to start to write, other than: write.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>Be Self Aware, Constantly</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I remember once I could write more than 4 pieces a night. There are more times I remember having difficulties to write a piece in 4 months. I call it the low days and the high days. When it happens, accept it. But also try to understand why it’s happening to you.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Ask yourself questions. Have you dedicate enough time to have a dialogue with yourself? Have you take enough time to actually sit still, and think about the things you’ve been through? Have you dedicate a little more time to make yourself comfortable with a pen and a notebook? Or a distraction-free writing app beside netflix?</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Low days and high days happen only because we decided (both intendedly or unintendedly) to put our focus on the things that surround us. It took a certain degree of self awareness to actually realize whether the things we give attention to, on a certain time period, will be beneficial in developing your writing.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>Lastly, put your inspirations down</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>In times of endless reference and inspiration, it’s always easy to get immersed in hours of book reading, blog reviewing, or youtube watching. We live in time where millions of good (and also bad) literature pop in front of our eyes wanting to inspire, or simply be seen.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Inspirations are good, but also acknowledge the fact that it consumes your attention. And your attention is the only thing that’s keeping you away from that blank page.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>A good book, or a good inspiration, also need to be put down. Because in the end, it silences your own voice. And your voice is the only thing that matter in your journey of writing, or word-crafting.</p>
</div>]]></description><link>http://gudhakesa.com/2016/10/07/a-beginners-writing-guide.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gudhakesa.com/2016/10/07/a-beginners-writing-guide.html</guid><category><![CDATA[words]]></category><category><![CDATA[ writing]]></category><category><![CDATA[ blogging]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Mahendra Gudhakesa]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[The 5 types of Millennials In The World]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>With myself belonging in the millennial generation, it&#8217;s always interesting for me to observe my own generation. It&#8217;s one of the ways I reflect back at myself, my decisions, and my view of life. And being involved in qualitative research often give me a profoundly general point of view in explaining my generation.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>What makes a millennial different compared to previous generations is the fact that we grew up with the internet. We millennials remember making our first email addresses, from services that are probably obsolete by now. We all experienced lifestyle changes through internet and technology, through gadgets and gizmos. Global connectivity is the excalibur to the modern day king Arthur, and I guess we&#8217;re the first generation who democratizes its full power.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>They way internet is changing our lives is by giving us two things. One, is the democratization of knowledge, and secondly is the disruption of our social conduct. Internet had enabled us to access information previously limited to certain cultures or countries. The birth of knowledge without boundaries had made us more critical than ever before. This of course, would affect how we live our social lives today. The way we interact with people is different compared to the young people in the 80s. We spend most of our times with friends, with our eyes glued to smarthphone screens. We could have lively discussions and chats without any lip movements, just a few tap of the thumbs.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>So, these democratization of knowledge, and disruption of social conduct. What do they bring us? Those things had brought us to a state where we&#8217;re naturally inclined to challenge any status quo or hegemony. We have access to vast amount of information now, so we challenge, we ponder, we tweak, we hack, and we question endlessly. Now that sounds like a millennial to me.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>There are no generation that have the drive to challenge the hegemony as hard as the millennials. This is due to the fact that the internet penetration among the global citizen is exponentially faster compared to other technological advancement.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>So most of millennials now have that call to change or challenge things. It&#8217;s more common for us millennials to argue with our parents or our teachers. We challenge institutions more openly, and we go as far as we can imagine. The conflict resolution between parents and millennial children had evolved into something unimaginable in previous times.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The question now is how do millennials cope or deal with that call to change and to challenge? Bearing that question in mind, here are the five types of millenials.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>The Straight Trajectories</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>These are the millennials who live their lives as if they&#8217;re living a straight line. The main key of living life for these straights are living life on repeat. They like to repeat success stories that are told to them, and live life accordingly. If my parents are lawyers, I&#8217;d get myself into law school too, because I know that being a lawyer is promising. If my parents say that working in a multinational company would benefit me, I&#8217;d do it. These millennials simply doesn&#8217;t embrace the true calling of being a millennial. They usually live their lives through the eyes and values of the previous generations.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Their simplistic, or somewhat naive approach to life is actually something we should give respect to. We have known that it&#8217;s harder than ever to keep life on track with different realities of modern days economy. These type of millennials work their way through career choices with ease and seamlessly. They&#8217;re the ones who had decided their direction of life before life even happens for them.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>The Anarchist</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>A polar example compared to the previous, this type of millennials focus their life on fighting against the current norm or hegemony. If society expect me to live in a certain way, the way I&#8217;m going to do it is act the other way around. If the way to live means having to indulge myself in a 9-to-5 jobs, to hell with it. These millennials will refuse to be bound by any rules or social conduct. They challenge everything in search for a better form of life. They embrace the call to change and challenge as their way of life.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Despite the anarchist nature of these types, they&#8217;re actually the most exposed to life experiments and opportunities. They are the first kind to create new things and able to make things happen. They make businesses happen, or making social impact heard. A lot of social revolution in world&#8217;s history came from these people unbound to rules and boundaries. There are huge probability that the next best thing in the world, comes from these type of millennials.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>The Compromiser</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>If life is like a circus act, then life for these millennials are like balancing a tightrope. They&#8217;re mainly focused on keeping balance between their inner calling as millennials, and maintaining society&#8217;s standard and expectation. A life form mostly found in emerging Southeast-Asian countries like Malaysia and Indonesia, but we might find these types lurking in most progressive cities of the world. These types often find themselves compromising their dreams in order to please certain social practices. These millennials see compromise as a way out. A balanced and proactive approach to life, with goals to please as many lives as possible; starting with their life, and other people that surrounds them.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>But it&#8217;s not entirely bad. One of the things we should appreciate from these type of millennials is their ability to manage multiple goals at once. They could be having a prestigious job in an international company, while also making businesses on the side. They&#8217;re the ones who is dying to change their way of life, while also being respectful to social norms and values.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>The Disconnected</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>A special case within millennials, these types resembles what most people remember being the punk-rock or emo kids in the early 2000s. These type of millennials usually have clear direction on where they want to go, but they don&#8217;t show it to others. They have this calling to challenge or to change, but they don&#8217;t preach about it. However, compliance to current society&#8217;s standard also not in their agenda. To most, they would seem like lost people. They tend to be reserved individuals to most.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>However, not everything is grim about these millennials. What we can learn from them are the willpower and endurance they had shown throughout their adolescent life. Though self-reserved, these types had proven to be the people who think and feel deeply. They face adversities in the most enduring way possible. Their perception towards life are inevitably useful and inspirational for other people in getting through life. Their story of perseverance and enduring life could prove to be meaningful for all of us.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>The Artist</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The last type of millennials, I often like to call the lucky ones. These are the rare types that usually made the world go round in their own orbit, effortlessly. The ones that have the calling to change and challenge, yet the world is conspiring with them in creating the changes they want to happen. These type of millennials usually doesn&#8217;t have much external factors to fight against in making their dreams happen. They simply have to be stubborn enough to do the things they love.  Things are provided, or easily come to their way. Their main challenge is self-reflective, and all about overcoming one&#8217;s own demon.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The way that they&#8217;re lucky, is because they usually could dedicate themselves fully on their road to self-development. They could be wanting different things compared to other people, yet the world gives them just that. They could be wanting to indulge their lives fully on the road to artistry and creation, or simply to have a job that society doesn&#8217;t want to have, yet they can do it with ease. For example, a son of a banker and investment broker who wanted to be a writer and scholar, and he worked his way through it with ease.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>In the end, there are no types of millennials better than the other. Eventually our own adversities and challenges shapes us the way we are today. And it&#8217;s no use for us to regret the things that happened to us in the past. Our challenges and calling only will shape our decisions the way it suits us. It&#8217;s important for us to understand well, which types do we belong to, to question ourselves, to reflect back on what made us into the millennials we are today. Eventually we&#8217;re required to combine forces together, shaping our world the way we envision it to be.</p>
</div>]]></description><link>http://gudhakesa.com/2016/10/07/The-5-types-of-Millennials-In-The-World.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gudhakesa.com/2016/10/07/The-5-types-of-Millennials-In-The-World.html</guid><category><![CDATA[words]]></category><category><![CDATA[ millennials]]></category><category><![CDATA[ generation Y]]></category><category><![CDATA[ qualitative]]></category><category><![CDATA[ research]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Mahendra Gudhakesa]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Learning To Be Present]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>I remember a few months ago, when I attended a workshop on drawing and painting. it was an open event, commissioned by local artists and painters for the general public. The main goal of the event is to introduce the fundamentals of drawing to the general public. The initiator of the events, the artists, believe strongly that anyone can draw, and it only takes a few correct approach to drawing to unleash the hidden talent in all of us.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>So they first open the workshop, telling us to draw a bowl of fruits in front of the room. And so I did. Of course I failed miserably. All I left on the piece of paper was a bunch of poorly-drawn bananas and oranges with incorrect order and shades.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I was later told that, the key for a successful, life-like drawings are when we perceive the object we&#8217;d like to draw just as it is, not as we thought it should be. I was dumbfounded at first, trying to make sense of whatever it is I have been told.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>But later on I got the point. My failure to draw is because I constructed bananas and oranges the way I remembered how bananas and oranges are shaped. I didn&#8217;t draw my bananas and oranges the way it is as presented in the bowl in front of me. I linger more on the shape of hundreds of bananas and oranges' I&#8217;ve seen, rather than the actual shape of the bananas and oranges in front of me.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>In my work as a qual researcher, I often got annoyed with a problem of not being able to understand why do people behave like they do. Why do people would use bing instead of google? Why do people like to eat tempe instead of tahu? It was always later I realized, the reason I am not able to understand them, is because I was actually asking: why don&#8217;t people behave like I do? If I am able to perceive the way people live the way they are, also with their realities and contexts, I would not have the same annoyance. I would make research reports better and faster and also made more sense.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>These series of things, which taught us to perceive things the way they actually are, in contrast to how we constructed the things based on our experience and memories, play a very important role in how we approach life. In specific, it taught us to deal with a happy life.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The key for a happy life is when we could perceive life as it is in front of us, not based on our constructed ideals and memories about the things that made us happy. Our previous excitements, memories, and experiences are constantly building aspirations and longings in the back of our head. These images and aspirations stays there, clouding our vision to really see life the way it is actually presented in front of our eyes. We fail to see a good life, because what we do is actually compare and contrast our current context with a previous reality that is obsolete.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>It is impossible to understand life as comprehensive as we might hoped, if we keep lingering on the good memories we had. Good things in the past happens because of the past&#8217;s context and reality. What we consider good in the past, could not possibly be as good if we experience it now, because we&#8217;re facing a different reality. We often seek happiness in life the way we expect a perfect deja vu moment of our previous exhilaration. While we all no, there is never a perfect deja vu moment in life.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>That is why, I think we should learn from artists, painters, photographers, or qual researchers. We should always be reminded that great beauty, or great reality, are always represented when we learn to be in the present. When we draw, copy, capture, or describe the current experience the way it is actually presented in front of us.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>In times of anxiety and anxiousness. It&#8217;s worth trying to get a bunch of bananas and oranges on a bowl, and try to draw it. Remember that we need to approach our current reality the way we draw the perfect bananas and oranges. By really making sense of what it really looks like in front of our eyes. Not by comparing them to previous bananas and oranges, and not by worrying about what our future bananas will look like.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Have a banana!</p>
</div>]]></description><link>http://gudhakesa.com/2016/10/07/Learning-To-Be-Present.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gudhakesa.com/2016/10/07/Learning-To-Be-Present.html</guid><category><![CDATA[words]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Mahendra Gudhakesa]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 07 Oct 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[In Appreciation of Dusk]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div id="post-image" class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="https://c1.staticflickr.com/9/8408/28951120124_e74ed9f610_b.jpg" alt="28951120124 e74ed9f610 b.jpg">
</div>
</div>]]></description><link>http://gudhakesa.com/2016/09/10/In-Appreciation-of-Dusk.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gudhakesa.com/2016/09/10/In-Appreciation-of-Dusk.html</guid><category><![CDATA[pictures]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Mahendra Gudhakesa]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 10 Sep 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Caught In The Middle]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>My dream to be a writer, or at least to constantly write, is actually a recent aspiration. I have developed my love for writing in my late university years. I remember it was my only way to express a late-teenage angst, and then the habit stick.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I love writing the way it function like an emotional outlet. Like a faucet for my overflowing emotions, thoughts and ideas. Writing is like taking my daily dose of drugs. Like an amphetamine, it helps me focus and lost at the same time. It keeps my mind afloat, yet my feet on the ground.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I am of course, lately in deep disappointment. Seeing my own writings to be not as productive as I hoped to be. And I kept wondering why, and how could this happen. So I contemplate.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Writing is like one important tool for one&#8217;s linguistic mastery. And linguistic mastery, for me, isn’t about communication per se. It’s about a discipline of thought. The way you manage your logic is detrimental to how you use language, and what language do you use.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I am, by default, a bilingual. In one side, I enrich my knowledge with English books and literature, yet I must function properly in most aspect of my life using my mother tongue. To some extent, I could feel the mastery of both language conflicts inside my head. And the conflict isn’t about diction or vocabulary, but more about point of views. The two language seem to have a polar thought structure. One rich in expression, the other functional. One heavy on analogy, the other rich in vocabulary. I often found myself confused and simply brain dead trying to retrieve words or threading sentences into a paragraph. Not only in writing, but also on verbal occasions.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I remember a research that mention human can’t really do, or focus at two things at one time. When it comes to the use of language, it does make sense. One can’t simply think and speak in two languages with different roots. Some people can speak english, while mixing up with a little french and Spanish. That’s understandable because those languages have the same root: Latin. The words different, the grammar different, but I can argue that all of those language share the same structure and discipline of thought. It was conceived out of cultures with many shared values.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I realised that maybe the fact that I’m stuck between two languages is the main barrier for my unproductive writing habit. I can’t seem to pinpoint words to use, or even usable expressions. I can’t decide clearly on how to narrate or describe a particular tone and point of views. I feel like my thoughts are caught in the middle.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I miss the moments where I could remember words flowing out of my fingertips seamlessly, faster than my tongue muster a syllable. I do miss the fluidity of words that runs in the back of my head each time I’m engage in a certain topic. It’s just that, now it isn’t happening. Or at least it’s not happening as often as I hoped it should.</p>
</div>]]></description><link>http://gudhakesa.com/2016/09/10/Caught-In-The-Middle.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gudhakesa.com/2016/09/10/Caught-In-The-Middle.html</guid><category><![CDATA[words]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Mahendra Gudhakesa]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 10 Sep 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Anxiousness of Being Home]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="paragraph">
<p>One Afternoon, in Ngurah Rai Int&#8217;l Airport</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>When we feel that we long for a significant other, or when we say we’re in love with a particular person, it is often a very revealing moment for ourselves. Often times, our attraction stems from appreciation of an idea, or attributes about them in which we are lacking. Our romantic tendency to long for someone are mostly based on the feeling of incompleteness we have towards ourselves.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Appreciation comes easy when we are faced with a person in which their quality excel far greater than we perceived ourselves to be. For example, we could appreciate someone who are good in self-financing, or perhaps very caring and warm. This is because we might be aware that those qualities are the things we do not really have. We might be a little clumsy in our finances, or perhaps we are often awkward and cold to new people. We long to complete ourselves, by finding the pieces we do not have.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Without we realising, our admiration or longing don’t always have to apply to our romantic partner. It could apply to anything. Like when we are longing for a new job, a new career, in deciding where to travel, or a new city to live in. We might be drawn into the beauty of old narrow streets in a European town, its warm afternoon, sidewalk cafes, and the laid-back ambience. We long for that, because we maybe living in a city with not much story of preserved heritage. It’s busy streets are deafening to our ears, the air polluted, and the way people live around us constantly remind us that we’re stuck in a rut.</p>
</div>
<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="http://67.media.tumblr.com/078c962c67eb709891174318f125c894/tumblr_inline_od0bimeoWQ1s8bhjl_540.jpg" alt="tumblr inline od0bimeoWQ1s8bhjl 540.jpg">
</div>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>In my recent travel to Bali, I can remember how I fell in love with everything this island have to offer. I remember how I wish I could spend my days in clean air, good breakfast, and have the view of the ocean in my wake. I thought of how I could take my time slowly and appreciate each day better, by watching the sunset at the end of each day. These are the thing I have been missing in my hometown, and I have developed my longing towards.
It is very easy for me to come into snap judgement and decisions about moving in to Bali. I could embrace a long term relationship with this island, fulfill my longing, fall in love, and commit myself on having my love affair with the beauty of the island.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>But then I remember, like two people who are able to fall in love, they are also able to fall out of love. When time does its magic towards our significant other, when it finally reveals them fully to us, we could suddenly, without our knowing think that we chose the wrong person. It is natural that the more we dedicate ourselves into a relationship, we realise we are eventually, irredeemably alone.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I finally understood that my longing for this island, are in fact an expression of the things I simply missed back home. There comes a realisation, that possibly, when the island life are fully revealed, it will give me another feeling of loneliness and anxiety. In the wake of my inevitable return from this trip, I have realised that I am anxious to bound back home. But I am just as anxious to imagine myself having to be committed, or in metaphor, to marry this island long term.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I came to this holiday trip, hoping to have a relief for my hometown anxiety. I haven’t got the things I wished for. I even came home with more fear and anxiety. But I also gained something more valuable: To accept the prevalence of anxiety that haunts each and every decisions we will made, and also the understanding of the logic behind our longing.
Like our love life. Love come and go easily. The feeling of longing happens easily only when we are reminded of the things we do not have. In the end, familiarity takes action and longing fades. We will wake up to the same boring reality of a long-term relationship, the duty of household financing, the unattractive prospect of laundry, or the repulsive aspect of our significant other’s character revealed across time. What is unchanged is our commitment to anchor ourselves in the reality (and security) we know will be our consequence to our long-term decision.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Just like my recent travel taught me, we have to be aware of the source of our longing. The things we long for might not be easily available nor accessible in one’s hometown, but that never means our dream destination always have everything we need. In the end, it’s important for us to anchor ourselves to the reality (and security) that no matter where we live, no matter where do we decide to stand our feet, the sun rises and sets in the same direction. The sea will always send its love with its waves. The mountains will still be as sublime to our perception.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>In short, no matter what the reality surrounds us, we could always anchor ourselves to the reality (and also security) that life continues in its own pace. Not the way we might hoped them to be, but always in its own beautiful, grandiose way.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Bali, September 2016</p>
</div>]]></description><link>http://gudhakesa.com/2016/09/10/A-Trevelers-Journal.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gudhakesa.com/2016/09/10/A-Trevelers-Journal.html</guid><category><![CDATA[words]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Mahendra Gudhakesa]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 10 Sep 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Why I Drive a 40-years-old Car, and What It Had Taught Me About Life]]></title><description><![CDATA[<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="http://66.media.tumblr.com/d9092d4d65765f334ad0bdb09800c628/tumblr_inline_noffhuK0Si1s8bhjl_540.jpg" alt="tumblr inline noffhuK0Si1s8bhjl 540.jpg">
</div>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Some summer afternoon, I drove my car into an intersection just in the heart of the city. The light turns red, so I slowed down, shift my gear down to first gear and release the clutch slowly in order to slow the car down. The brakes of the car aren’t something you could put your trust on, and it’s extremely noisy if you force it through. I was on front, just right behind the stop line.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The car doesn’t have any stereo set whatsoever, so the slow purr of the engine was all I can hear for my entertainment. It’s a steady hum-and-shackle just below 1,000 RPM and the occasional hiccups. An occasional surge of fuel surplus going thought the carburettor because of the new additional fuel pump I have to install in order to keep the car running.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>As the light turns green, I carefully shift to the first gear, and release the clutch. Accelerating was not really an instant effect you could expect. It’s a slow and steady push forward as you heard the engine start purring at higher RPM, and the occasional horn-honking drivers right on your back. You can’t help it. You just have to move along, slow and steady, with the melodies of diminished, high-pitched electrical horn honking at the back of your head.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The acceleration of the car was pretty much slow, with its engine blowing hiccups and mechanical tantrums. Even at top gear, you could only go as fast as 3,000 RPM without having to worry that the whole assembly of the car might just tear down. It never goes faster than 90 km/h, and I don’t think it’s wise to try to go further than that.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The overal ride experience was strenuous. The suspension doesn’t work at all, due to its old-and-worn rubber cones on all 4 wheels. One single bump you encounter, could provoke an earthquake right behind the driver’s seat. And the big “thunk” sound of metal-to-metal contact was never a good part of your driving experience.
The car was a perfect, ingenious design back in its time. But then again, after 40 years of constant service, it’s an entirely different story.</p>
</div>
<div class="imageblock">
<div class="content">
<img src="http://66.media.tumblr.com/c3746698b9d6ddd29f3ea252beff8e29/tumblr_inline_noffigqw2s1s8bhjl_540.jpg" alt="tumblr inline noffigqw2s1s8bhjl 540.jpg">
</div>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I’ve been driving a 1974 Mini Cooper on a daily basis throughout my professional career (my professional career wasn’t that long up until this article is written, though). I could say that this is the first car that I have taken responsibility caring for. I’ve never gotten my hands dirty trying to maintain a car my whole life, until this baby came in to my posession.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The car was undeniably a sight of beautiful assymetry and a satirical approach to imperfection. Ingenious in design, practical, with its heart lies on the foundation of marvelous craftmanship, but it has its limits. Its functionality stripped down comfort, and its simplicity lacks sympathy to its drivers.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>But it was through driving this car, I learned a lot to listen, and to sympathise</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>The car lacks sympathy, it was the other way around. The car had turned into something that I have to sympathise for if I ever want to drive around with it everyday. Gas-guzzling, engine revving, or excessive speeding weren’t a logical choice for me. I have to sympathise to every worn-out gear and gaskets that 40 years of service had given them. Even a masterpiece often had time to work  against its nature, and I have to understand that. Driving around with the car had made me more sensitive to my senses. It reminds me to pay attention to how the clutch responded to the gentle push of my toes. It taught my ears to listen carefully to any possible out-of-place clunk and thump. Personifying the car to be people I deal with everyday, reminds me that I might have do the same to the people around me. I realised that other people often were bunch of emotional and physiological gears and gaskets too, worn-out by experience and time of their own. It taught me to listen more to their story, and to sympathise more to what they have to say.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>I learned that bumps and obstructions are a given in life. Just be cautious.</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Bumps and roadblocks aren’t something I could take for granted when driving a car with a worn-out suspension system. I can’t put my foot on the right pedal without having to be sure of any obstruction ahead. The road wasn’t in my favour, and I don’t think it ever will be. The road is beyond what I can control, so I just let it be. The whole experience taught me to be a little more cautious in driving. Maybe that goes the same with life. Roadblocks and detour weren’t really within our controls. Problems and trivia aren’t really within our grasp to make sense of. What’s more important is for you to be cautious of what might lies ahead. I guess it’s more important than ever to cast your eyes about to whatever within your visibility. Be mindful of what lies ahead. You’ll dodge bullets if you’re lucky.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>I learned to slow down, I learned to be small</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I think the correct expression to define the experience using an old car is to be “in appreciation of slowness”. It’s a common sight having to drive at the slowest lane and see all cars and trucks overtake you. It’s the same with life, I guess. It’s always a common sight to see other people succeed, thrive, or march forward a little faster than you think you are. It makes me realise, that often it’s pretty much pointless if you have to force yourself up to their pace. You were given your own pace and speed, to do your own thing. And often, the best response you can give to the fast-forwarding people and world around you, is just to slow down, be small, and don’t hurt yourself. It’s not getting ahead that matters. It’s about reaching your destination. It’s not about how fast you’ll get there, it’s more about how you enjoy your time planning the journey. You have the burden (or benefits) of carrying a 40-years-old wisdom right within your palms, and there’s no need of forcing it through the traffic. Be small, slow down, and enjoy the ride.</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><strong>I learned about love</strong></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>Kahlil Gibran once said,</p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p><em>“Love is work made visible. And what is it to work with love? It is to weave the cloth with threads drawn from your heart, even as if your beloved were to wear that cloth.”</em></p>
</div>
<div class="paragraph">
<p>I guess this car is a perfect definition of love. My tendency to objectify my love for the car is more than just a blind, testosterone-filled passion. It’s more about realising the true exchange of love. It took inconsiderable amount of time and care to maintain a well-running, old engine on wheels. I learned that for you to get the most out of the whole experience, it took lots of heartfelt care and patience to make sure it’s running flawlessly. What the car gave me in return was also something that was important beyond measure. It’s my means of transportation, a means of keeping my world up and running. And the experience of it all, which has been a thrill, never fail to deliver that triumphant feeling.
Eventually, after all the effort, blood, and endless bath in engine oil, It’s more about realising and understanding the feeling of being loved back. Your efforts are returned, visibly. You feel the result of all the care you put through right in the grasp of your palms, at the touch of our feet. Your patience are paid back in the sweet hum of that 1.000cc engine.
You reap the seeds you sow with your own hands. You get what you give. And for me, that’s the true exchange of love humankind had ever experienced.
I learned to appreciate life (and beauty) a little bit better, and life is more about the journey
What are the perks of having to be slow and small? It’s no other than the chance to catch more of the world’s marvel, beauty, and diversity. It often took me twice as long to get to one place or another compared to other people. But I realised what had not been missing. The thrill, the view, and the sight of the world surround me were always at my pleasure. The journey to a destination had given me a chance to cast my sight around and about, to whatever the world is trying to show me. The joy of the journey often lies just right at the side of the road, and you only can enjoy every marvel of it by paying more attention to what it has to offer. Roadside sight, wasn’t a thing I take for granted anymore.
What are more exciting in life other than to be right here, in the now? The beauty of life isn’t on the end of the road, on top of mountains, or in the very end of your destinations. It was the grassy field you met along the hike. It was all the small lake you stopped by during your first checkpoint. It was the people you met along the way, giving thumbs up, smiled, and laughed with you along your ride. It was the children laughing, cheering your way up, although you’re struggling to put the second gear on the long ascending road.
In slowness, you learn to laugh with your efforts. To make fun of the things you had put your heart on doing, and share the joy with other people along your way.
And I guess those are the things I learned about life, through driving an outdated, 40-years-old engine on wheels. Sometimes, you just gotta pay attention on the little things. But most of the time, you’ll realise that some things just take time. You can’t force things to go your way. You have to live a little of your life along with the bump. You’ll learn that you can’t run all the time. You’ll learn to appreciate slowness, and dwell in it. It taught me to sit back and breathe. Perfection comes with patience and determination. And in the end, no one will deny beauty made with care and time.</p>
</div>]]></description><link>http://gudhakesa.com/2016/08/24/Why-I-Drive-a-40-years-old-Car-and-What-It-Had-Taught-Me-About-Life.html</link><guid isPermaLink="true">http://gudhakesa.com/2016/08/24/Why-I-Drive-a-40-years-old-Car-and-What-It-Had-Taught-Me-About-Life.html</guid><category><![CDATA[words]]></category><category><![CDATA[ cars]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Mahendra Gudhakesa]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2016 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>